In this episode we will have a look at the first level of protostar from exploit-exercises.com.
在这一集中，我们会从 exploit-exercises.com 中 protostar 的第一级开始查看。
If you have questions about the setup, you can watch the previous video.
如果您对安装与设置有疑问，可以观看上一个视频。
Generally I advise you to stop the video right here, and work on it by yourself first.
一般来说，我建议你在这里停止视频，并自己尝试一下。
Maybe give it a day and see how much you can figure out.
也许花一天时间，看看你能弄清多少东西。
And after that, watch my explanation.
在之后，看我视频中的解释。
But if you feel completely lost, then just follow me.
但，如果你确实完全迷路了，那就跟上我，我带你出去。
This here should give you enough information to solve the next level on your own.
这视频应该给你足够的信息，让你独自解决下一等级的问题。
So let’s first have a look at the challenge description.
所以，让我们先看看挑战的描述。
This level introduces the concept that memory can be accessed outside of its allocated region,
这一级别引入了一个概念，就是可以在分配(内存)的区域之外，访问内存，
how the stack variables are laid out, and that modifying outside of the allocated memory
栈变量的布局方式是怎么样的，以及在分配之外的内存，
can modify program execution.
能通过 modified 程序执行，进行修改。
And this level is located at /opt/protostar/bin/stack0
这一级位于 "/opt/protostar/bin/stack0"
Ok.
好啊。
Next we will have a look at the source code which is provided below.
接下来我们将看到，下面提供的源代码。
Let’s start with a first quick overview.
让我们先从快速概述，开始。
This is clearly a program written in C. It reads some input with gets(), then checks
这显然是一个用 C 编写的程序。它用"get()"读取一些输入，
the modified variable and prints either a success or fail message.
然后检查 modified 变量，并打印成功或失败消息。
So obviously the goal of this level is to make the program print the success string.
所以显然，这个级的目标是，让程序打印成功字符串。
Note, this level is not about executing arbitrary code to gain root privileges.
注意，这个级不是执行任意代码，以获得根权限。
First we have to understand a couple of basics.
首先，我们必须了解一些基本知识。
A real full root exploit will come in later levels.
一个真正的完整的根攻击，将出现在后面的级别问题。
So for now, let’s focus on this smaller goal.
现在，让我们关注这个小目标。
We can also execute the stack0 program.
我们也可以执行 stack0 程序。
And we can see that it seems to wait for some input, and then prints “Try again?”.
我们可以看到它似乎在等待一些输入，然后打印“再试一次？“。
Ok so let’s have a more detailed look at the code.
好的，让我们更详细地看看代码。
There are two local variables.
有两个局部变量。
An integer number modified, and a char array buffer with space for 64 characters.
一个整数 modified ，以及一个可容纳 64个字符的字符数组缓冲(buffer)。
An array of chars in C is basically just a string.
C 中的字符数组，基本上只是一个字符串。
Then modified will be set to 0.
然后 modified ，设置为 0。
And apparently never changed changed.
显然，并没有改变。
Next is the gets function with our 64 character long char buffer.
接下来是，带有64个字符长字符缓冲的 gets 函数。
Let’s have a look at the gets man page.
让我们看一下“gets”手册页。
So gets is used to read a string from the input.
所以，这个 gets 是可以从输入中，读取字符串。
When we scroll down we can also find a Bugs section, which is telling us, to never use
当我们向下滚动时，我们还可以找到一个 Bugs 部分，
gets()!
这部分(情况下)，告诉我们永远不要使用 gets()！
This cannot be more clear that this is the vulnerability in this program.
不能再清楚啦，这是该 gets 的漏洞。
As an explanation it says, that it’s impossible to tell how many characters gets will read.
这里解释一下，它说，gets 不可能知道会读到多少个字符。
It has been used to break computer security.
这，能被用来破坏计算机安全。
And after the gets call, modified is compared to 0.
在 gets 调用之后，会将 modified 与 0 进行比较。
If it is not 0, we have won.
如果不是 0，我们就赢了。
But how can modified ever become non zero?
但是，modified 要怎么样，才能永远不为零？
It’s set to 0 and never changed.
把它设为 0，且从不更改。
btw. the volatile is a way to tell the compiler, that it should not optimize the usage of this
顺便说一句，volatile 是会告诉编译器，它不应该优化，这个变量的用法。
variable.
变量。
Because at first glance it looks like modified will always be 0 and thus it might simply
因为乍一看，它看起来 modified 的值总是 0，
remove the unnecessary if-case.
因此它可能只是，移除不必要的 if-case。
But with volatile we can force the compiler to keep it as it is.
但是，使用 olatile，我们可以强制编译器保持原样。
I think we have a good understanding of this program now in C. Let’s open it with gdb
我想，我们现在对 这个 C程序，有了很好的理解，让我们用 gdb 打开它吧。
and start debugging.
开始调试。
First let’s set a breakpoint in main with break *main.
首先，让我们用 break *main ，在 main 中，设置一个断点。
Then type run or short r to start the program from the beginning.
然后键入 run 或 r 简写，从头开始启动程序。
Now it stopped at the start of main.
现在它停在 main 的起点。
With disassemble you can disassemble the current function.
使用反汇编可以，反汇编当前函数。
But also set the disassembly-flavor to intel, because I like it more.
但同时，也将反汇编风格设置为 Intel，因为我更喜欢它。
Let’s try to understand fully what is happening here.
让我们试着了解，这里发生的完整过程。
I ignored those parts in my reverse-engineering introduction, but here we need to fully understand
在逆向工程介绍中，我忽略了这些部分，
how the stack works.
但这里我们需要完全理解栈的工作方式。
So let’s start with the first instruction ‘push ebp’.
那么让我们从第一条指令“push ebp”开始。
A quick flashback to my CPU introduction video.
然后，对我的 CPU 介绍视频，来个快速闪回印象。
I mentioned that the stack is just a memory area at the bottom.
我提到栈，只是位于底部的一个内存区。
When we look at the mapped memory with ‘info proc mappings’, we can see that the stack
当我们用'info proc mappings'，查看映射的内存时，
goes from bffeb000 to c0000.
我们可以看到栈，从 bffeb000 到 c0000。
And because the stack grows from the bottom, it starts at the highest address.
因为栈从底部往上增长，所以，它从最高地址开始(数起)。
c0000 doesnt belong to it anymore, so basically the stack starts at c0000-8. which is bfffff8.
c0000不再属于它，所以基本上来说，栈是从 c0000-8 开始。也就是 bffff8。
So push EBP.
而，push ebp。
EBP is a register which is used as the base pointer.
ebp是一个寄存器，用作基本指针。
And it contains an address pointing somwhere into the stack.
它包含一个，指向栈中某个位置的地址。
esp right now is actually bffff7bc.
esp现在实际上是 bfff7bc。
And at that position is this b7something value.
在那个位置是这个 b7 某值。
Ok so whatever the meaning of this address is, it seems to be important, because it get’s
好吧，不管这个地址的意思是什么，它似乎很重要，
pushed on the stack.
因为它推入栈上。
Which is like saving the value.
这就像，保存值(变量)一样。
And at the end of the main function you find a leave.
在 main 函数结束时，你会找到一个 leave。
And the intel instruction reference tells us that leave is just basically a mov esp,
英特尔指令参考告诉我们，leave 基本上只是一个 mov esp，
ebp and pop ebp.
push ebp 和 pop ebp。
As you can see the start and end of a function is symmetrical.
如您所见，函数的开始和结束是对称的。
At the start we push ebp and mov esp into ebp.
开始时，我们将 push ebp ，以及移动 mov ESP 进入 ebp。
And when the function is done, we do the reverse.
当函数完成后，我们做相反的操作。
Don’t worry, I will illustrate this nicely in a moment.
别担心，我一会儿会，好好说明这一点。
Just one more little thing.
还一件小事。
After those two instructions we mask esp, which basically just sets the last 4 bits
在这两条指令之后，我们 mask esp，它基本上，
to 0, to keep it nicely aligned.
只设置最后 4位 为0，使其保持对齐。
Not that important.
没有很重要啦。
And then we subtract hex 60 from it.
然后我们从中，减去(subtract) hex 60。
So ESP, the stack pointer now points to a bit lower address than ebp.
所以 ESP，栈指针现在指向比 ebp 低一点的地址。
And the next instruction moves a 0 at the memory location at offset hex 5c from the
而下一条指令，是移动一个0，到
stack pointer.
与栈指针偏移 hex 5c 的内存位置。
And that seems to perfectly match our modified variable that gets set to 0.
这似乎与我们被设置为 0 的 modified 变量完美匹配。
At first it’s a lot to take in.
一开始，要接受很多知识，确实不容易。
But let’s do it again but this time with an animation.
但，我们可以再来一次，而这次是配上动画。
So here on the left you can see the assembler code.
所以在左边，你可以看到汇编代码。
And on the right I will illustrate the stack. with the 3 important registers, the instruction
在右边，我将展示这个栈。使用3个重要寄存器，
pointer EIP, the stack pointer ESP and the base pointer EBP.
指令指针 eip 、栈指针 esp ，和 基指针 ebp。
So first it starts somewhere else with a ‘call main’.
所以首先，它从另一个地方开始，有一个“call main”。
Call will push the theoretically next instruction pointer onto the stack.
调用（call）会将理论上的下一个指令指针，推到栈上。
And then jump to our main function.
然后，跳到我们的 main 函数。
As you can see, when the address of the next instruction was pushed, the stack pointer
如您所见，当下一条指令的地址被推入后，
got incremented and the address placed there.
栈指针增加了地址。
So now comes our .
所以，现在是 push ebp 登场。
I will illustrate with some arrows that this value is a stack address, which points to
我将用一些箭头，说明这个值是一个栈地址，
another location on the stack.
它指向栈上的另一个位置。
Now we overwrite EBP with the value from ESP. mov ebp, esp.
现在我们用"mov ebp, esp"，让 esp 的值覆盖 ebp。
Then we subtract hex 0x60 from esp.
然后从 esp 中，减去 hex 0x60。
Look at the stack now.
现在，再看看这个栈。
This area between esp and ebp is called a stack frame.
这个介于 esp和ebp 之间的区域，称为栈帧。
This is now a small area of memory, that we can use for local variables and calculations
现在，这就是一小块内存，我们可以用来，
inside the main function.
在 main 函数中进行局部变量和计算。
And do you notice where EBP is pointing to?
你注意到 ebp 指向哪里了吗？
It’s pointing to the OLD ebp.
它指向，*旧的* ebp。
So this area here is basically the stack frame of the previous function, which called main.
所以，这里的区域，基本上是前一个函数的栈帧，它叫 main。
And we know that we move 0 into esp+0x5c.
我们还知道，我们把 0 移动到 esp + 0x5c。
Which we think is the modified variable.
我们认为，这是 modified 变量。
And that’s true.
事实说明，我们是对的。
The local variables all have their space in this stack frame.
局部变量在这个栈帧中，都有自己的空间。
And it’s so big, because it had to make space for at least 64 characters and the modified
但它太大了，因为它必须留出至少64个字符
integer.
和一个 modified 整数的空间。
At the end of this function we will now perform a leave.
在此函数结束时，我们将执行 leave。
Which moves EBP into ESP.
将 ebp 移动到 esp。
Effectively destroying the previous stack frame.
有效地销毁以前的栈帧。
Then we pop EBP, which restores the previous stack frame.
然后我们 pop ebp，它将恢复先前的栈帧。
Isn’t that amazing?
神奇吧？！
But WAIT! it gets cooler.
但是等等！还有更酷的。
How do we now know where to return to from main?
我们现在怎么知道，main 的返回是到哪里？
Well if you remember, call pushed the address of the instruction after the call.
如果你还记得的话，call 会在自身调用后，推指令的地址进栈。
So the next value on the stack is where we want to return to.
所以栈中的下一个值，就是我们想要返回的位置。
And the ret instruction is basically just popping this address into the instruction
而 ret 指令基本上，就是把这个地址 pop（弹出），
pointer.
送入指令指针。
And thus jumping back where we came from.
然后跳回我们来的地方。
Computers.
计算机（Computers）。
ha! aren’t they mindblowing.
哈！它们真是爆裂。
So much smart stuff in there.
里面，有太多聪明的东西。
Now let’s continue with the assembler code.
现在，让我们继续使用汇编程序代码。
After a value on the stack got set to 0, we prepare the eax register with an address from
在栈上的一个值，设置为0之后，我们准备好 EAX寄存器，
the stack at offset 0x1c.
接收，栈偏移量为 0x1C 的地址。
LEA (load effective address) is similar to a move, but instead of moving the content
lea（加载有效地址）类似于移动，但不是
of an register offset into a register, it moves the address of an register offset into
将寄存器偏移量的内容，移入寄存器，而是
a register.
将寄存器偏移量的地址移入寄存器。
And this address then get’s placed at the top of the stack.
然后这个地址被放在栈顶。
This is called calling convention.
这叫做 调用约定。
The programs and functions have to agree how to pass function parameters in assembler.
如何在汇编程序传递函数参数，这一命题，程序和函数必须达成一致。
In this case the parameters are placed on the stack.
在这种情况下，参数被放置在栈上。
And the gets function takes one parameter, which points to a character buffer. and the
gets函数接受一个参数，该参数指向一个字符缓冲区。
character buffer is on the stack, thus we have to pass it the address where the character
以及字符缓冲区是在栈上的，因此我们必须将，
buffer starts.
字符缓冲区所在的开头地址，传递给它。
Afterwards we read the value we previously set to 0, and with test we can check if it
然后我们读取之前设置为 0 的值，通过测试，
is 0 or not.
我们可以检查它是否为0。
And branch off to print one of the messages.
然后进入分支，打印其中一条消息。
So let’s remove the breakpoint form main with ‘del’ delete and set a breakpoint
因此，让我们用“del”，删除 main 的断点，
before and after the gets.
并在 gets 之前和之后，设置一个断点。
Before we restart, I want to show you a cool trick.
在我们重新开始之前，我想给你看一个很酷的技巧。
We will define a hook, that will execute some gdb commands when we stop at a breakpoint.
我们将定义一个钩子，可当我们在一个断点停止时，执行一些 gdb 命令。
To do this type define hook-stop
输入定义的 hook-stop，来做到这一点。
then info registers to show the registers and x/24wx $esp.
然后“info registers”显示寄存器和 x/24wx $esp。
and x/2i $eip and finish with end.
和 “x/2i $eip”，结束。
This will now print the registers, the stack and the next two instructions every time when
现在每次我们遇到了一个断点，
we hit a breakpoint.
都会打印 寄存器，栈和下两个指令。
Now restart the program.
现在重新启动程序。
Boom. first breakpoint.
栋。第一个断点。
Now continue and enter a couple of capital A’s.
现在，继续输入几个大写字母 A。
Do you see those hex 41s. those are all the As you have entered.
你看到那些 hex 41s 了吗？这些都是你输入的 A。
Now let’s see the content of the address we check if it’s 0.
现在，让我们看看地址的内容，我们检查它是否为0。
Simply examine $esp + hex 5c.
只需检查 $esp + hex 5c。
Still 0.
仍为 0。
But it shows us where it is located on the stack. and when we look at our stack, we see
但它告诉我们它在栈上的位置。当去看我们的栈时，
that our As are still a little bit too far away.
我们看到我们的 A 们，还是有点太远了。
So let’s count how much we need.
让我们来计算一下，我们需要多少。
4 characters here.
这里有 4个字符。
Then 4 times 4 that’s 16 for a row.
然后是，4次 乘以 4，就是16。
And we have 3 full rows.
我们有三排。
And with the next full row we can apparently write into those zeroes.
在下一整行中，我们可以明显地，写进这些零。
So run again.
所以，再次运行。
Enter that many characters.
输入，这么多字符。
I like to use recognizable patterns.
我喜欢使用，可识别的模式。
So I can clearly see which letter which row is.
所以我可以清楚地看到，哪一行是哪个字母。
looks promising.
看起来很实在。
So a single step forward, and it will load the modified variable from the stack into
所以向前迈出一步，它会将 modified 变量，
eax.
从栈加载到 EAX
And indeed.
确实如此。
Those are the characters that we entered.
这些是我们输入的字符。
Let’s try this without gdb.
让我们在没有 gdb 的情况下，试试这个。
We can use echo and our previous string and pipe it into the stack0 program.
我们可以使用 echo 和 前面的字符串，并将其传输到 stack0 程序中。
Cool! it worked.
酷！它奏效了。
Before we end, let me show you how we can make the input a bit more convenient thanks
在我们结束之前，让我向您展示一下，如何使输入更加方便。
to python.
谢谢 Python。
With python -c we can specify a command that should be executed.
使用 python -c，我们可以指定，应该执行的命令。
Then we can use print and pythons cool string syntax which allows us to repeat this character
然后我们可以使用，print 和 python 的酷字符串语法，
multiple times.
它允许我们多次重复这个字符。
With this knowledge you should be able to solve stack1 and stack2.
有了这些知识，您应该能够解决 stack1 和 stack2 。
It’s pretty much the same task, just with some different ways of input and a different
因它几乎是相同的任务，只是有一些不同的输入方式，
vulnerable function.
和一个不同的脆弱函数。
But if you invest some time, you can absolutely solve it.
但是如果你花点时间，你完全可以解决它。
And I will not make a video about those.
我不会录制一个关于这些的视频。
Next video will be about stack3.
下一个视频，将是关于 Stack3 的。
This is when things start to get juicy.
这是'水果'，开始变得多汁的时候。
See you next time!
下次见！